<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Notes</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 21:24:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 21:24:06 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Lecture notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[A polymer ("many parts") is a macromolecule consisting of many monomer units covalently bonded together to form a long chain.
Naming: Use the prefix "poly" followed by the monomer name (e.g., polyethylene). Brackets are required for complex names like poly(vinyl chloride). Oligomers: Molecules with a molecular weight () g/mol. Polymers: Molecules with g/mol. Types: Polymers can be organic, inorganic, natural (like DNA), or synthetic (like PVC or Polystyrene) .
Polymers can be synthesized in various 3D shapes at the molecular level:
Linear Ring, Star, Comb, or Ladder. Dendrimers: Highly branched, well-defined structures with a central core, repetitive branching units, and a terminal surface.
Dendrimers are highly branched polymers with a well-defined structure.
They're tricky to synthesise at large quantities due to having difficult to protect active site.
<img alt="Dendrimers.png" src="images/dendrimers.png" target="_self">
Dendrimers can be synthesised via divergent (centre out) or convergent (surface inward) synthesis.Modern polymer science distinguishes between two primary mechanisms:<br>However they're some exceptions to this such as <a data-href="#Ring-Opening Polymerization (ROP)" href="lecture-notes.html#Ring-Opening_Polymerization_(ROP)_0" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ring-Opening Polymerization (ROP)</a> which can produce a heteroatom backbone via a chain-growth mechanism.Unlike small molecules, polymers have a distribution of chain lengths.
Number-average (): The total mass of all molecules divided by the number of molecules. This is the most frequently used average. Weight-average (): Based on the mass fraction; larger molecules contribute more to this average. Relationship: is always greater than . Dispersity (): Calculated as . It indicates the breadth of the mass distribution; for all polymers, .
The represents the number of monomer units in the average chain._(Where is the molecular mass of the monomer).Polymers are not linear; they adopt a loosely coiled ball shape due to bond angles and rotational freedom.
Bond Angles: C-C bonds (0.154 nm) exist at an angle of 109°. Rotational Conformations: Chains rotate around bonds into stable (trans: 180°, gauche: 60° or 300°) or unstable (cis: 0°) states. Shapes: A chain of 20,000 carbons has possible shapes.
There are three main types of isomerism that dictate polymer properties: Stereoisomerism (Tacticity): Concerns the arrangement of chiral centres within the backbone. Atactic: Random arrangement; usually amorphous. Isotactic: All substituents on the same side; semi-crystalline helix. Syndiotactic: Alternating sides; semi-crystalline zig-zag or helix. Regioisomerism: Concerns how monomers join, typically head-to-tail. Head-to-head joins are infrequent. Geometrical Isomerism: Occurs in diene polymers (e.g., isoprene) as cis or trans configurations around a double bond. Example: Cis-polyisoprene is natural rubber (elastomer), while trans-polyisoprene is gutta-percha (rigid). Most commercial polymers are semi-crystalline, containing both ordered (crystallites) and disordered (amorphous) regions. A polymer can never be 100% crystalline. Higher crystallinity generally increases strength.
Glass Transition Temperature (): The temperature where amorphous regions change from glassy to rubbery as segments of the backbone have enough energy to rotate. It appears as a change in slope on a specific volume graph. Melting Temperature (): The temperature where crystalline domains lose structure and melt. It is a sharp transition. Relationship: always.
The response of a polymer to deformation (Compression, Tension, Shear, Torsion) is measured as a Modulus.
Young’s Modulus (): Calculated from a stress-strain curve as . Material Types: * Brittle: High stress, low strain at break (e.g., polystyrene). Plastic: Yield point followed by deformation (e.g., polypropylene). Elastic: Low modulus, high strain (e.g., rubber). The Glass Transition Temperature () is a property associated exclusively with the amorphous regions of a polymer. It marks the transition from a hard, brittle "glassy" state to a soft, flexible "rubbery" state due to rotation in the backbone.
Backbone Rotation: represents the onset of backbone rotation, where individual segments of the polymer chain gain enough thermal energy to rotate freely. Below : Chains are "frozen" in place, resulting in a glassy material. Above : Chains can rotate, allowing for rubbery behaviour.
Any aspect of the polymer structure that hinders backbone rotation will increase :
Backbone Stiffness: Rigid linkages (like aromatic rings) increase significantly.
Substituent Polarity: Stronger intermolecular forces (e.g., hydrogen bonding in poly(vinyl alcohol)) increase .
Steric Hindrance: Large, bulky side groups (like the benzene ring in polystyrene) restrict rotation and raise .
Side Chain Flexibility: Longer, flexible side chains (e.g., in poly(alkyl methacrylates)) can actually decrease by increasing "free volume".
Tacticity: The spatial arrangement of substituents has a small but definite effect on .
The Crystalline Melting Temperature () is the temperature at which crystalline domains lose their ordered structure and melt. is governed by a balance of interchain forces and chain flexibility:
Hydrogen Bonding: Polyamides (nylons) and polyurethanes have high because hydrogen bonds effectively "tie" chains together. Dipole Interactions: Polyesters lack H-bonding but have dipole-dipole interactions, resulting in moderate . Chain Regularity: Highly symmetrical and linear chains (like High-Density Polyethylene, HDPE) pack more efficiently, promoting higher crystallinity and stable . The "Odd-Even" Effect: In polyamides and polyesters, chains with an even number of carbon atoms in the repeat unit often pack better and have higher than those with an odd number.
Polymers are semi-crystalline, meaning they consist of ordered crystalline regions (crystallites) embedded in a disordered amorphous matrix.
Unit Cell: The smallest repeating unit of the crystal19. Polymer unit cells are often large and complex due to chain restrictions.
Lamellae: Crystalline "sheets" formed by chains folding back and forth. In reality, chains often leave one lamella to entangle in amorphous regions before entering another.
Spherulites: Large, spherical structures visible under a microscope, composed of many lamellae radiating from a central nucleus.
The degree of crystallinity ( or ) is the percentage of the polymer that is in crystalline regions.va = Vol of 100% amorphous polymer.
vs = Vol of sample measured.
vc = Vol of 100% crystalline polymer.
The volume is calculated by 1/density.Crystallization occurs in two stages: nucleation (forming a stable "seed") and growth (adding chains to the nucleus).
Homogeneous (Sporadic): Nuclei form randomly. Heterogeneous: Growth is "seeded" by foreign particles (dust, nucleating agents). This allows for the control of spherulite size; more nuclei lead to smaller spherulites, which improves mechanical properties.
The kinetics are described by the Avrami Equation, which relates the fraction of uncrystallized polymer () to time ():
: Avrami rate constant. : Avrami exponent, which indicates the geometry of the growth unit (rod, disc, or sphere) and the type of nucleation. Nucleation is random throughout the volume of the polymer melt.
There is either hetero or homogeneous formation of nuclei.
The geometry is specific and fixed for the duration of the crystallisation process.
There is a linear growth rate for a single dimensions, (G=growth constant).
The phases have constant densities that remain unchanged throughout the crystallisation process.
Step polymerisation involves the reaction of monomers with at least two chemically reactive groups (e.g., A-A + B-B or A-B). Common examples include the synthesis of polyesters, nylons, and polyurethanes.
Process: Growth occurs through the combination of any two species: . Conversion: High molecular mass is only achieved at very high conversion of functional groups (), small by-products should be removed to drive higher conversions.
The relationship between the extent of reaction () and the degree of polymerisation () is defined by:
Equilibrium: Many step reactions (like esterification) are reversible. To achieve high , by-products (e.g., ) must be removed to drive the equilibrium to the right. Stoichiometric Imbalance: If one reagent is in excess, the is limited. This is described by the ratio of monomer a to b: Molar Mass Dispersity (): As , the dispersity approaches 2.0. This is known as the "most probable distribution".
Chain polymerisation proceeds via the sequential addition of monomers to an active centre (free-radical, anion, or cation). Initiation: Creation of active centres using chemical initiators (e.g., AIBN, BPO), UV, or radiation. Initiator efficiency () accounts for radicals lost to side reactions like the "cage effect". Propagation: Rapid growth as monomers add to the active chain end. Termination: Growth stops when two active centres react. Combination: Two chains join (common for styrene); . Disproportionation: Hydrogen atom transfer creates one saturated and one unsaturated chain (common for methacrylates); . High molecular weight chains are achieved early in the reaction. Increasing initiator concentration increases the reaction rate but decreases the resulting molecular weight.
Suspectable to chain transfer, forming side products.
unwanted long side chains can be formed when a chain bonds in the middle of another chain's backbone.
Retarders react with radicals to form a product that is incapable of further growth.
Highly effective retarders are called inhibitors and can be added to monomers to prevent spontaneous polymerisation in long-term storage then remove via distillation.
Anionic: Involves anionic active ends that cannot react with each other, leading to "living" polymerisation with no inherent termination. This allows for excellent control over molecular mass (). Cationic: Extremely fast but suffers from high rates of termination and chain transfer, offering poor control over molecular weight. Uses transition metal catalysts (e.g., ) and co-catalysts (e.g., ). Advantage: Produces highly stereoregular polymers (e.g., isotactic polypropylene) and linear, high-density polyethylene. Dispersity: Typically has very broad molecular weight distributions () due to multiple active site types. Polymers can be synthesised using various physical formats depending on the need for heat control and viscosity management.Non-linear polymers are created by introducing monomers with a functionality () greater than 2.
Branched Polymers: Soluble structures formed when the number of branchers per chain is low. They have lower solution and melt viscosities than linear polymers of the same mass. Gels (Networks): Insoluble, crosslinked structures formed when branching exceeds a critical point.
The extent of reaction at which an infinite network (gel) forms can be calculated using the average functionality ():
Functionality Factor (): The average number of functional groups per monomer unit in the initial mixture. Critical Conversion: Example: If , gelation occurs at ( conversion). Controlled polymerizations are specialized chain reactions designed to produce polymers with highly predictable molecular weights and narrow molecular weight distributions (low dispersity).
Low Dispersity: Typically (often referred to as monodisperse). Linear Growth: The molecular weight increases linearly with monomer conversion. Living Character: Active chain ends remain functional after 100% conversion, allowing for "one-pot" block copolymer synthesis through sequential monomer addition. Suppressed Termination: In Controlled-Radical Polymerization (CRP), termination is suppressed (though not eliminated) relative to the rate of propagation. In "pure" Controlled Polymerization (CP), termination is effectively eliminated.
A form of controlled polymerization where the active chain end is an anion.
Initiation: Uses initiators like n-butyl lithium () to form an anionic adduct. Propagation: Anionic chain ends do not react with each other, meaning there is no inherent termination. Conditions: Requires rigorous purification of monomers and solvents to remove protic impurities (like ) and high vacuum ( Torr) or inert atmospheres. Monomers: Requires electron-withdrawing groups (e.g., , , or aromatic rings) to stabilize the anionic charge.
For an ideal anionic polymerization (100% conversion), the degree of polymerization () and molecular weight () are calculated as: Concept: A trialkylsilyl group is transferred along the chain during propagation. Application: Primarily used for acrylates and methacrylates. Pros/Cons: Less stringent conditions than anionic (no high vacuum needed), but difficult to achieve very high molecular weights ( g/mol). Concept: Cyclic monomers (lactones, lactams, cyclic ethers) are "opened" to relieve ring strain. Mechanism: Can be anionic, cationic, or radical depending on the initiator. Utility: Excellent for producing biodegradable polymers like polyesters.
ATRP is a versatile CRP technique that uses a transition metal catalyst to control radical growth.
Dormant vs. Active: Chains spend most of their time in a "dormant" halide-capped state (). Equilibrium: A Copper(I) catalyst/ligand complex reversibly abstracts the halogen to create a "reactive" polymer radical () for propagation. Components: Requires an alkyl halide initiator, a monomer (styrenics, methacrylates, acrylates), and a transition metal catalyst (typically Cu, Fe, or Ru) with solubilizing ligands.
RAFT is a CRP technique that relies on a dithioester-based Chain Transfer Agent (CTA) to maintain living character.
Mechanism: Rapid, reversible transfer of a group between dormant and active chains. Control: The target depends on the concentration of the CTA, not the initiator (). Versatility: Works under bulk, organic, and aqueous conditions and is tolerant of many functional groups (including acids).
Characterization techniques are used to measure the different molecular weight averages () and chemical composition.GPC, also known as Size Exclusion Chromatography (SEC), separates polymer chains based on their size in solution.
Process: A polymer solution is pumped through columns packed with porous beads. Mechanism: Smaller molecules enter the pores and take longer to elute; larger molecules bypass the pores and elute first. Detectors: Generally uses Refractive Index (RI), Viscosity, or UV detectors.
Used for several critical calculations: Calculation: Comparing peak areas of initiator/end-protons to backbone protons.
Polymerization Kinetics: Following the disappearance of monomer vinyl peaks over time to calculate % conversion.
Copolymer Composition: Determining the molar and volume fractions of different blocks in a copolymer.
]]></description><link>lecture-notes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">AI Gen/Lecture notes.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 21:18:30 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/dendrimers.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/dendrimers.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>